Finding Aid for the Will Ella Tatom Johnson Smith and James Mapheus Smith Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Will Ella Tatom Johnson Smith and James Mapheus Smith Papers
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0403
8.4 linear_feet
Biographical Note
Will Ella Tatom Johnson Smith was born December 11, 1890 in Union City, Tennessee. Will Ella was one of four children born to Kate Kirkmon Tatom and William Clinton Tatom. Her father, Colonel William Clinton Tatom was co-owner and publisher of the Ohioan Democrat.
James Mapheus Smith was born October 4, 1901 in Clarksville, Tennessee to Mattie Rudolph and G. Tandy Smith. He received his B.A. from Southwestern University in Clarksville, Tennessee, taught high school for a short time and then went to graduate school. In 1928 he received his M.A. in Sociology from Vanderbilt University and in 1931 graduated with a Ph.D. all the while teaching courses at the university.
Will Ella was a librarian at Vanderbilt University from 1922 to 1931. She married James Mapheus Smith in Paducah, Kentucky on July 25, 1923. In 1931 she and Mapheus moved to Lawrence, Kansas where he had obtained a position as an Assistant Professor of Sociology. Will Ella and Mapheus stayed in Kansas until 1943 when they moved to Washington D.C. so that Mapheus could work for the Selective Service System. They stayed in Washington till 1966 when Mapheus retired from government work.
Upon retirement Will Ella and Mapheus moved back to Nashville, Tennessee where they bought a house on Blair Avenue and settled into retired life. Mapheus died January 5, 1968 of a heart attack. As a memorial to him Will Ella made a gift to Vanderbilt University to have the identification plaques made for the trees on campus.
After his death Will Ella lived for almost twenty years devoting herself to gardening, genealogy, and writing articles for the local papers. Will Ella died April 15, 1986.
Scope and Content Note
The Will Ella Tatom Johnson Smith and James Mapheus Smith Papers consist of approximately seven cubic feet of material. The bulk of the papers consist of subject files, writings by Will Ella and James Mapheus, and writings by their associates.
The Will Ella Tatom Johnson Smith Papers are comprised of five series and represent almost half of the total collection. The series for Will Ella Tatom Johnson Smith are:
1. Correspondence
2. Writings
3. Personal
4. Subject Files
5. Writings By Others
The Correspondence series consists of Will Ella’s outgoing correspondence dating from 1959 to 1979 and her incoming correspondence arranged alphabetically. A bulk of the outgoing correspondence is to James Summerville, who in 1990 donated the letters to Vanderbilt Special Collections with the provision they be added to the Will Ella Tatom Johnson Smith Papers.
The Writings series represents only four files but does contain an interesting account of her early life and of her poetry.
The Personal series comprises accumulations of genealogy on the Tatom family, newspaper clippings, legal documents, and memorabilia. The memorabilia portion of this series contains some nice antique cards and poetry programs.
The Subject Files series is the largest portion of Will Ella’s papers, it is broken down further into four sub-series: General Files; Authors/Acquaintances; Vanderbilt University; and Associates. These are primarily clipping files on subjects that Will Ella had an interest, they span a number of years but are mainly from the 1940’s to the 1970’s.
Writings by Others series is comprised of the manuscript Hyperakmos Woman by Eric Tatom, Will Ella’s brother and by a manuscript of poetry by Saville Clark.
The James Mapheus Smith Papers are comprised of four series and are located in the second half of the Will Ella Tatom Johnson Smith and James Mapheus Smith Papers. The four series are:
1. Correspondence
2. Personal
3. Writings
4. Newspaper Clippings
The first series of the James Mapheus Smith Papers consists of three files of correspondence; the outgoing correspondence is arranged alphabetically as is the incoming correspondence.
The Personal series contains legal, financial, and biographical information on J. Mapheus Smith and his life. This series also contains a number of resumes and job descriptions from the many jobs he had over his life.
The Writings series has been broken down further into six sub-series: Book Reviews; Manuscripts; Articles; Writings by Others; Class Assignments; and Lecture Notes. The manuscripts in this collection are Smith’s Eminent Men, Social Psychology, and a two volume work entitled World War II Administrative History: Bureau of Aeronautics Summary (this is physically located at the end of the collection) also included in this sub-series are his M.A. and Ph.D. theses. A broad range of off-prints and full journals containing Smith’s articles comprise the largest portion of this series. Writings by Others sub-series consists of articles and bibliographies by Smith’s peers. The Class Assignments and Lecture Notes sub-series are from Smith’s sociology classes and cover his teaching career from 1927 to 1950.
The Newspaper Clipping series was probably maintained by Smith’s wife, Will Ella though it appears in Smith’s papers. These clipping files are on John F. Kennedy and his family and have primarily been pulled out of magazine and newspapers. Of interest in this series is a "J.F.K." coloring book. Another collecting emphasis of Will Ella was the early history of George Washington, this can be seen in the scrapbook containing clippings on the history and restoration of Washington’s Mount Vernon.
- Will Ella Tatom Johnson Smith Correspondence
  - Correspondence--Outgoing, March 13, 1959-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence--Incoming A (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence--Incoming B (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence--Incoming C (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence--Incoming D (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence--Incoming E-G (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence--Incoming H-J (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence--Incoming K-L (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence--Incoming M-R (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence--Incoming S-Sa (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence--Incoming Sb-Sz (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence--Incoming Ta (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence--Incoming Tb-Tr (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence--Incoming U-Z (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence—Writings—Personal
  - Correspondence--Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence--Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence--Unsent (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Writings--Poems (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Writings--Speeches (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Writings--Reminiscences (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Writings—Reminiscences (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Writings -Untitled (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Writings --Untitled (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Personal--Award (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Personal--Capitol Hill South East Citizens Association (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Personal--Legal Documents (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Personal—Family Genealogy Tatom, Absalum Nathaniel (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Personal—Family Genealogy Tatom, Eric J. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Personal—Family Genealogy Tatom, William Clinton (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Personal--Family- Genealogy-Miscellaneous. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Personal--Clippings- Newspaper and Magazines (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Personal--Memorabilia- Poetry Programs (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Personal--Memorabilia- Post Cards (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Personal--Memorabilia- Theatre Programs (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Personal—Memorabilia -Antique Cards (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Personal--Memorabilia- Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Subject Files-Series
  - Benjamin, Judah Phillip (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Black Americans (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bridges, Covered (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Caldwell, Rogers Clark (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Campbell, George W. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Carter, Jimmy 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Carter, Jimmy 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Carter, Jimmy 1980-n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Carter, Lillian (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Carter, Rosalynn (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Civil War (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Davidson, William Lee (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Georgia (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Georgia, Savannah (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Henry, Patrick (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - James, Jesse (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Jefferson, Thomas (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Kentucky (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Ku Klux Klan (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Lafayette, General (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Louisiana (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Maryland (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - McCall, Willis (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Mississippi (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Mountains, Great Smokies (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - North Carolina (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - South Carolina (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Templeton, John (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Tennessee-- Boswell, George Worley (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Tennessee-- Civil War (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Tennessee-- Gore, Albert, Sr. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Tennessee-- Handy, W. C. (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Tennessee-- Harris, Hugh Pate (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Tennessee-- Haywood, John (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Tennessee-- Highlights of the Volunteer State (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Tennessee-- Historic Landmarks Association (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Subject Files -Series One Continued
  - Tennessee-- Homes (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Tennessee-- Hooker, John J. Nov. 1968-Sept. 1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Tennessee-- Hooker, John J. Oct. 1970-Nov. 1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Tennessee-- Jackson, Andrew (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Tennessee-- Melungeons (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Tennessee-- Nameless (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Tennessee-- Nashville (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Tennessee-- Nashville -Gaul, Gilbert (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Tennessee-- Nashville -Williams, Albert (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Tennessee-- Readyville (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Tennessee-- Rugby (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Tennessee-- Tennessee Valley Authority (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Tennessee-- Tennessee -Misc. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Virginia-- Alexandria (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Virginia-- Blair, James (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Virginia-- Churches (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Subject Files -Series One Continued
  - Virginia-- Colonial (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Virginia-- Homes (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Virginia-- Jamestown (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Virginia-- Monticello (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Virginia-- Mount Vernon (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Virginia-- Richmond (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Virginia-- Smith, John (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Virginia-- University of Virginia (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Virginia-- Williamsburg (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Virginia-- Yorktown (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Virginia-- Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Weltner, Charles Longstreet (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Subject Files -Authors/Acquaintances -Series Two
  - Agee, James (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Aiken, Conrad (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Bandy, William T. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Cheney, Brainard (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Davidson, Donald (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Dickey, James (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Dykeman, Wilma (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Elliott, William Yandell (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Elliston, Joseph Thorp (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Faulkner, William (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Fitzgerald, F. Scott (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Frank, Isadore Small (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Frierson, William C. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Fugitives-Agrarians (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Haley, Alex (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Hirsch, Sidney Mttron (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Horn, Stanley (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Hunt, Robert B. (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Ingram, Bowen (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Subject Files -Authors/Acquaintances -Series Two Continued
  - Jarrell, Randall (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Jones, Madison, Jr. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Kefauver, Estes (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Lee, Harper (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Lytle, Andrew (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - McGill, Ralph (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Mitchell, Margaret (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Moore, John Trotwood (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Moore, Merrill (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Morgan, Berry (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Morgan, Marshall (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - O’Conner, Flannery (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Odum, Howard (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Olmstead, Frederick Law (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Percy, Will (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Patton, Frances Gray (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Porter, Katherine Anne (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Ransom, John Crowe (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Rawlings, Marjorie Kinnan (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Rayford, Julian (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Roberts, Elizabeth Madox (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Street, James Howell (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Stuart, Jesse (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Tate, Allen (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Taylor, Peter (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Warren, Robert Penn (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Weeden, Maria Howard (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - West, Richard S. (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Wigginton, Eliot (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Williams, Tennessee (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Wills, Jesse (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Wolfe, Thomas (Box 6, Folder 32)
- Subject Files Authors/Acquaintances -Series Two Continued
  - Anderson, John Q. (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Arnow, Harriette Simpson (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Avary, Myrta Lockett (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Beals, Carleton (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Beatty, Richmond Coom (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Bradbury, John M. (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Brehm, H.C. (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Burt, Jesse C. (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Campbell, Harry Modean (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Chestnut, Mary Boykin (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Clark, John Henry (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Connelley, William Elsey (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Cornwell, Ilene J. (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Coulter, E. Merton (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Cowan, Louise (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Crabb, A. L. (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Craddock, Charles Egbert (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Dowdey, Clifford (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Dupree, Robert S. (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Edwards, India (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Flood, Charles Bracelen (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Ford, Jessie Hill (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Ford, Maddox Ford (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Foster, Ruel E. (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Glasgow, Ellen (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Goodspeed’s History of East Tennessee (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Gordon, Caroline (Box 6, Folder 59)
- Subject Files -Authors/Acquaintances -Series Two Continued
  - Green, Ely (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Green, Fletcher M. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Greene, Lee S. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Harris, George Washington (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Harvard, William C. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Hero, Alfred O., Jr. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Hill, Doris Moss (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Hume, Ivor Noel (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Izard, Barbara (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Jones, Katherine M. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Jarrell, Hampton M. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Karanikas, Alexander (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Kendall, Lucy (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Lewis, E. C. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Lewis, Meriwether Liston (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Luskin, John (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Mass, Peter (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Manchester, Paul (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Martin, Harold H. (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - McDonough, James Lee (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Meriwether, Elizabeth Avery (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Mifford, Jessica (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Mizener, Arthur (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Morrissey, Ralph G. (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Oates, Stephen B. (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Owsley, Frank L. (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Percy, Walter (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Phillips, Harry (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Price, Reynolds (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Purdy, Rob Roy (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Rubin, Louis D. (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Scott, Evelyn (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Shores, Louis (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Smith, J. Frazier (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Smith, Lee (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Stampp, Kenneth M. (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Stern, Phillip Van Doren (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Stewart Randall (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Stowe, Harriett Beecher (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Styron, William (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Summerville, James (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Swint, Henry Lee (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Tucker, Edward L. (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Unterecker, John (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Wade, John Donald (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Warren, John W. (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Wade, Richard C. (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Watson, Robert (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Weaver, Richard M. (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Wicker, Tom (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Wiley, Bell Irvin (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Witten, George (Box 7, Folder 52)
- Subject Files -Vanderbilt University -Series Three
  - Aden, John M. (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Allen, Lou Willa (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Archer, Verley Mae (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Beard, Louise A. (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Bell, Eric, Jr. (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Cheney, Frances (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Clark, Saville Trice (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Curry, Walter Clyde (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Duncan, Edgar Hill (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Elledge, W. Paul (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Friends of the Library: Vanderbilt University (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Gertrude Vanderbilt and Harold S. Vanderbilt Literary Symposium (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Harrelson, Walter (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Haun, Mildred (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Heard, Alexander (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Heard, Jean (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Jean and Alexander Heard Library (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Joint University Libraries: Vanderbilt University (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Kirkland Hall (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - McGill, John T. (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Mims, Edwin (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Nixon, Herman Clarence (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Paine, Thomas F., Jr. (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Pascal Pia Collection (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Robinson, Francis A. (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Starr, Alfred (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Seay, James (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Smith, Kelly Miller (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Stevenson, Alec B. (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Sullivan, Walter L. (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Vanderbilt, Harold S. (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Vanderbilt Television New Archive (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Vanderbilt University: Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Vanderbilt University Theatre (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Vanderbilt Visiting Writers Program (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Vanderbilt, William H. (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Walker Management Library (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Waller, James M. (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Warren, Rosanna (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Watts, Charles (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Wesley Hall (Box 7, Folder 93)
- Subject Files Associates -Series Four
  - Aiken, Mary (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Bobula, Ida (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Derwood, Gene (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Eliot, T. S. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Franklin, Louis (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Gore, Jeanne Guerrero (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Hankin, Gerald T. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Kirkman, Keith (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Lowell, Robert (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Salerno, George (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Spender, Stephen (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Thayer, Schofield (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Wagstaff, Blanche Shoemaker (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Werm, Gaston (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Williams, William Carlos (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Williams, Oscar (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Writings -Others
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Table of Contents (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Table of Contents and Introduction (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Chapters 1-3 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Chapter 4 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Chapter 5 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Chapter 6 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Chapter 7 (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Writings -Others —James Mapheus Smith -Personal
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Chapter 8 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Chapters 9-12 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Chapters 13-14 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Chapters 15-17 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Writings -- Tatom, Eric Hyperakmos Woman Chapter 18 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Writings -- Clark, Saville - Poetry (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - James Mapheus Smith (Box 9)
- Correspondence -Personal
  - Correspondence-- Outgoing A-Z (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence-- Incoming A-H (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence-- Incoming I-Z (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Personal - Biographical Clippings (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Personal -- Financial -- Household and Government (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Personal -- Legal Documents (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Personal -- Publications -- Bibliography (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Personal -- Resumes and Job Descriptions (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Personal - Sketches/Drawings (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Personal -- Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 16)
- J. M. S. --Writings Book Reviews --Manuscripts
  - Writings -- Book Reviews (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Table of Contents (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter I (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter II (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter III (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter IV (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter VI (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter VII (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter VIII (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter IX (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter X (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter X (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter XI (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter XII (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter XIII (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter XV (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter XV (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter XVI (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Chapter XIX (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Eminent Men Misc. (Box 10, Folder 20)
- J. M. S. --Writings --Manuscripts
  - Writings -- Clippings -- Eminent Men (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Introduction-Chapter III (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapters I-III (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapters IV-V (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter VI (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter VII (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter VIII (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter IX (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter X (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XI (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XII (Box 11, Folder 11)
- J. M. S. --Writings --Manuscripts
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XIII (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XIV (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XV (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XVI (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XVII (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XVIII (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XIX (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XX (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XXI (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter XXII (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Table of Contents Bibliography & Research Notes (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapters IV-V (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Writings -- Manuscript -- Social Psychology Chapter VI-VII (Box 12, Folder 13)